<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
  <title lang="cze">Plán pro univerzální slabičnou segmentaci</title>
  <title lang="eng">A Roadmap for Universal Syllabic Segmentation</title>
  <author order="1">Sojka, Ondřej</author>
  <author order="2">Sojka, Petr</author>
  <author order="3">Máca, Jakub</author>
  <language>eng</language>
  <summary lang="cze">Prostorově a časově efektivní segmentace (dělení slov) přirozených jazyků zůstává jádrem každého sázecího systému, ať už jde o TeX, webový prohlížeč nebo mobilní operační systém. Ve většině jazyků je dnes pragmaticky preferováno slabičné dělení reflektující výslovnost při čtení.

Vzhledem k tomu, že přepínání jazyků často není v textech označeno, renderovací stroj (webový prohlížeč či TeX) potřebuje univerzální slabikovou segmentaci. V předloženém článku ukazujeme proveditelnost této myšlenky tím, že nabízíme prototypové řešení dvou hlavních problémů: A) použití Patgenu ke generování vzorů pro několik jazyků najednou; a B) neexistence podpory Unicode v nástrojích jako Patgen nebo TeX (vzory v kódování UTF-16).

Pro A) jsme ke generování univerzálních slabičných vzorů použili seznamy slov devíti slabičných jazyků (čeština, slovenština, gruzínština, řečtina, polština, ruština, turečtina, turkmenština a ukrajinština). Pro B) jsme vytvořili verzi Patgen, která používá datovou strukturu Judy array, a porovnali její efektivitu s implementací trie.

S údaji z těchto devíti jazyků ukazujeme, že: A) vyvinutí univerzálních, obecných slabičných vzorů s vysokým pokrytím je možné, a to s velkým dopadem na prakticky všechny sázecí stroje včetně webových prohlížečů; a B) podpora Unicode znaků ve vzorech dělení slov v programech TeX a Patgen je možná pomocí Judy array.</summary>
  <summary lang="eng">Space- and time-effective segmentation (word hyphenation) of natural languages remains at the core of every document rendering system, be it TeX, web browser, or mobile operating system. In most languages, segmentation mimicking syllabic pronunciation is a pragmatic preference today.

As language switching is often not marked in rendered texts, the typesetting engine needs universal syllabic segmentation. In this article, we show the feasibility of this idea by offering a prototype solution to two main problems: A) Using Patgen to generate patterns for several languages at once; and B) lack of Unicode support in tools like Patgen or TeX (patterns in UTF-16 encoding) is missing.

For A), we have applied it to generating universal syllabic patterns from wordlists of nine syllabic, as opposed to etymology-based, languages (namely, Czech, Slovak, Georgian, Greek, Polish, Russian, Turkish, Turkmen, and Ukrainian). For B), we have created a version of Patgen that uses the Judy array data structure and compared its effectiveness with the trie implementation.

With the data from these nine languages, we show that: A) developing universal, up-to-date, high-coverage, and highly generalized universal syllabic segmentation patterns is possible, with a high impact on virtually all typesetting engines, including web page renderers; and B) bringing wide character support into the hyphenation part of the TeX suite of programs is possible by using Judy arrays.</summary>
  <lang_summary>eng</lang_summary>
  <doi>10.5300/2023-3-4/125</doi>
  <category>informatics</category>
  <range_pages>125-138</range_pages>
</article>
