<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article doi="125" language="en" publication_type="full_text"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <titles>
    <title>A Roadmap for Universal Syllabic Segmentation</title>
  </titles>
  <contributors>
    <person_name contributor_role="author" sequence="first">
      <given_name>Ondřej</given_name>
      <surname>Sojka</surname>
    </person_name>
    <person_name contributor_role="author" sequence="additional">
      <given_name>Petr</given_name>
      <surname>Sojka</surname>
    </person_name>
    <person_name contributor_role="author" sequence="additional">
      <given_name>Jakub</given_name>
      <surname>Máca</surname>
    </person_name>
  </contributors>
  <pages>
    <first_page>125</first_page>
    <last_page>138</last_page>
  </pages>
  <additional-content>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Space- and time-effective segmentation (word hyphenation) of natural languages
        remains at the core of every document rendering system, be it <TeX/>, web browser,
        or mobile operating system. In most languages, segmentation mimicking syllabic
        pronunciation is a pragmatic preference today.
      </para>
      <para>
        As language switching is often not marked in rendered texts, the typesetting
        engine needs universal syllabic segmentation. In this article, we show the
        feasibility of this idea by offering a prototype solution to two main problems:
        A) Using Patgen to generate patterns for several languages at once; and
        B) lack of Unicode support in tools like Patgen or <TeX/> (patterns in UTF-16
        encoding) is missing.
      </para>
      <para>
        For A), we have applied it to generating universal syllabic patterns from
        wordlists of nine syllabic, as opposed to etymology-based, languages (namely,
        Czech, Slovak, Georgian, Greek, Polish, Russian, Turkish, Turkmen, and Ukrainian).
        For B), we have created a version of Patgen that uses the Judy array data
        structure and compared its effectiveness with the trie implementation.
      </para>
      <para>
        With the data from these nine languages, we show that:
        A) developing universal, up-to-date, high-coverage, and highly generalized
        universal syllabic segmentation patterns is possible, with a high impact on
        virtually all typesetting engines, including web page renderers; and
        B) bringing wide character support into the hyphenation part of the <TeX/> suite
        of programs is possible by using Judy arrays.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <title>Plán pro univerzální slabičnou segmentaci</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Prostorově a časově efektivní segmentace (dělení slov) přirozených jazyků zůstává
        jádrem každého sázecího systému, ať už jde o <TeX/>, webový prohlížeč nebo mobilní
        operační systém. Ve většině jazyků je dnes pragmaticky preferováno slabičné dělení
        reflektující výslovnost při čtení.
      </para>
      <para>
        Vzhledem k tomu, že přepínání jazyků často není v textech označeno, renderovací
        stroj (webový prohlížeč či <TeX/>) potřebuje univerzální slabikovou segmentaci.
        V předloženém článku ukazujeme proveditelnost této myšlenky tím, že nabízíme
        prototypové řešení dvou hlavních problémů:
        A) použití Patgenu ke generování vzorů pro několik jazyků najednou; a
        B) neexistence podpory Unicode v nástrojích jako Patgen nebo <TeX/> (vzory
        v kódování UTF-16).
      </para>
      <para>
        Pro A) jsme ke generování univerzálních slabičných vzorů použili seznamy
        slov devíti slabičných jazyků (čeština, slovenština, gruzínština, řečtina, polština,
        ruština, turečtina, turkmenština a ukrajinština). Pro B) jsme vytvořili verzi
        Patgen, která používá datovou strukturu Judy array, a porovnali její efektivitu
        s implementací trie.
      </para>
      <para>
        S údaji z těchto devíti jazyků ukazujeme, že:
        A) vyvinutí univerzálních, obecných slabičných vzorů s vysokým pokrytím je
        možné, a to s velkým dopadem na prakticky všechny sázecí stroje včetně
        webových prohlížečů; a
        B) podpora Unicode znaků ve vzorech dělení slov v programech <TeX/> a Patgen je
        možná pomocí Judy array.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </additional-content>
  <xi:include href="citations.xml"/>
</article>
